Monday Musical Club; Records apap089
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Monday Musical Club Records
1924-1988
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap089
15.02 cubic ft. processed to date
The Monday Music Club was formed in 1904 among twenty women, to practice their music skills. The women practiced their skills in workshops and other artistic excerices. Even though they were founded in 1904, the collection does not cover the first twenty years of the club.
Acquisition Information
The initial items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by Agnes Armstrong and other members of the Monday Musical Club prior to 1992. Following the dissolution of the Club, Ray Andrews donated a small amount of additional material in 2025.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Administrative History
The Monday Musical Club was organized for women in Albany, New York in 1904 with twenty members to study, discuss and perform music in an informal manner. The Club's purpose was to encourage a broader culture in Music and Art among its members and in the community at large. Opportunities were available to members to participate in workshops, artist programs, and the chorus. The workshops were held in members' homes and allowed members to perform for each other in a social setting to develop the talent and repertoire of participants. The artist programs provided monthly solo performances for those who qualified. The chorus rehearsed weekly and provided a learning experience under the direction of a conductor and in public performance. The Club chorus formed in 1917 to present two concerts a season.
The Club began holding benefit programs in 1906 and continued to hold benefit programs for many years including during World War II. The Altruistc Committee was active at different times in the Club's existence and oversaw the presentation of benefit programs and performances for shut-ins and charitable organizations. Lecture recitals and illustrated talks on musical talks were popular among early members along with musical performances. The Club was at times associated with the National and State Federation of Music Clubs during the 1930s and 1940s and joined the United Arts League (later the Albany League of Arts) in the Capital District in 1947. Membership in the League continued through the 1980s. The Club sponsored a junior girls group of music students ages 13 to 18 called the Music Makers as well as the Young Musicians Forum, which was organized in 1977. The Club dissolved in 2023 after more than a century of existence, sending its music to the Thursday Musical Club in Schenectady.
Scope and Contents
The records of the Monday Musical Club most strongly document the group's performances and activities. The Club's programs and yearbooks provide a comprehensive list of performances from the 1950s through the 1980s. The annual yearbooks are a rich source of information including club membership, performances, and financial status. The Club's history before 1950 is documented through only scattered items. The Club's administrative functions are documented through meeting minutes and reports submitted to committees as well as the Club. The minutes cover the years from 1939 through the 1960s, while reports are available for the 1960s and 1970s. The scrapbooks are a rich source of Club history using programs, yearbooks, and new clippings with occasional photographs, club newsletters, or related materials. A small number of images are available for viewing online from the University at Albany Libraries' Digital Collections database.
The collection does not include musical scores for pieces performed by the Club. The meeting minutes and reports are incomplete and no additional records were deposited in the Department after the initial transfer of records.
Additional material including treasurers' records and programs from club events for the period 1924-1934 are available at the Albany Institute of History and Art's Library.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1: Administration, 1939-1984
Series 2: Programs and Yearbooks, 1924-1987
Series 3: Scrapbooks and Audiovisual, 1926-1988
All subjects arranged alphabetically and series 3 is arranged by format.
Music; Albany, New York; Women--Societies and clubs; Women in nonprofit organizations; Albany (N.Y.); Scrapbooks; Newsletters; Administrative records; Membership; Minutes; Programs (documents); Financial Records; Photographs; The Woman's Club of Albany; New York State Federation of Women's Clubs
- Administration, 1939-1984; Undated; 1; 0.33 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  The Administration Series includes records created by the Club during the operation of its usual activities and programs include committee reports, newsletters, and meeting minutes, which compose the bulk of the series. There is a small amount of correspondence as well as versions of the Club's constitution and by-laws..
  - Anniversary and Historical, 1954-1983 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 1)
  - Business Patrons, 1981 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 2)
  - Constitution and By-laws, 1951; 1975/1984 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1983; 1987 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 4)
  - Membership Application, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 1939-1953 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 6)
  - Minutes, 1953-1954 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 7)
  - Minutes, 1958-1975 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 8)
  - Minutes, 1964-1978 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 9)
  - Newsletter, 1962-1984 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 10)
  - Publicity, 1950-1984 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 11)
  - Reports, 1962-1978 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 12)
  - Survey, 1968 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 13)
  - Tribute to Sherlie Wheeler Harpham, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 14)
- Programs and Yearbooks, 1924-1987; 2; 0.33 cubic ft.
  - Programs, 1924-1952 (Box 1 (2-Series 2:Programs and yearbooks), Folder 15)
  - Programs, 1953-1959 (Box 1 (2-Series 2:Programs and yearbooks), Folder 16)
  - Programs, 1960-1967 (Box 1 (2-Series 2:Programs and yearbooks), Folder 17)
  - Programs, 1968-1974 (Box 1 (2-Series 2:Programs and yearbooks), Folder 18)
  - Programs, 1975-1979 (Box 1 (2-Series 2:Programs and yearbooks), Folder 19)
  - Programs, 1980-1985 (Box 1 (2-Series 2:Programs and yearbooks), Folder 20)
  - Programs, 1986-1988 (Box 1 (2-Series 2:Programs and yearbooks), Folder 21)
  - Programs, Others, 1940; 1975-1979 (Box 1 (2-Series 2:Programs and yearbooks), Folder 22)
  - Yearbooks, 1937-1954 (Box 1 (2-Series 2:Programs and yearbooks), Folder 23)
  - Yearbooks, 1954-1960 (Box 1 (2-Series 2:Programs and yearbooks), Folder 24)
  - Yearbooks, 1960-1968 (Box 1 (2-Series 2:Programs and yearbooks), Folder 25)
  - Yearbooks, 1968-1980 (Box 1 (2-Series 2:Programs and yearbooks), Folder 26)
  - Yearbooks, 1980-1986 (Box 1 (2-Series 2:Programs and yearbooks), Folder 27)
  - Young Musicians Forum, 1982-1986 (Box 1 (2-Series 2:Programs and yearbooks), Folder 28)
- Scrapbooks and Audiovisual, 1926-1988; 3; 1.61 cubic ft.
  - Branscome, Gina, 1971 (Box 1 (3-Scrapbooks and Audiovisual), Folder 29)
  - Newsclippings, 1941-1986 (Box 1 (3-Scrapbooks and Audiovisual), Folder 30)
  - Photographs, 1948-1986 (Box 1 (3-Scrapbooks and Audiovisual), Folder 31)
  - Scrapbook, 1926-1967 (Box 1 (3-Scrapbooks and Audiovisual), Folder 32)
  - Scrapbook, 1936-1946 (Box 1 (3-Scrapbooks and Audiovisual), Folder 33)
  - Scrapbook, 1936-1946 (Box 1 (3-Scrapbooks and Audiovisual), Folder 33)
  - Scrapbook, 1942-1974 (Box 1 (3-Scrapbooks and Audiovisual), Folder 34)
  - Scrapbook, 1942-1974 (Box 2 (3-Scrapbooks and Audiovisual), Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1949-1950 (Box 2 (3-Scrapbooks and Audiovisual), Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook, 1950-1951 (Box 2 (3-Scrapbooks and Audiovisual), Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook, 1967-1982 (Box 2 (3-Scrapbooks and Audiovisual), Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook, 1974-1980 (Box 2 (3-Scrapbooks and Audiovisual), Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook, 1974-1980 (Box 2 (3-Scrapbooks and Audiovisual), Folder 6)
  - Scrapbook, 1980-1984 (Box 2 (3-Scrapbooks and Audiovisual), Folder 7)
  - Scrapbook, 1984-1988 (Box 2 (3-Scrapbooks and Audiovisual), Folder 8)
  - Scrapbook, Original, 1949-1950 (Box 2 (3-Scrapbooks and Audiovisual), Folder 9)
  - Slides, 1976-1977 (Box 2 (3-Scrapbooks and Audiovisual), Folder 10)
  - Scrapbook Original, 1926-1967 (Box 3 (3-Scrapbooks and Audiovisual), Item 1)
  - Scrapbook Original, 1936-1940 (Box 3 (3-Scrapbooks and Audiovisual), Item 2)
  - Scrapbook Original, 1950-1951 (Box 4 (3-Scrapbooks and Audiovisual), Item 1)
  - Scrapbook Original, 1980-1984 (Box 5 (3-Scrapbooks and Audiovisual), Item 1)
  - Scrapbook Original, 1984-1988 (Box 5 (3-Scrapbooks and Audiovisual), Item 2)